<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno tertio Henrici Octavi The kynge our soueraygne lorde Henry the eyght ...</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9362.1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898709</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898709</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 419:19 or 2023:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno tertio Henrici Octavi The kynge our soueraygne lorde Henry the eyght ...</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Powell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1563?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from Beale; no complete copy seen.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁶ I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Contains years 3-7. Years 4-6 each have separate title page; register is continuous. Each title page has border with Greek key design (McKerrow &amp; Ferguson 26).</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 419:19 identified as STC 9362+++.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 419:19 is "Anno quinto" only.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22324:1"/>
            <head>ANNO QVARTO HENRICI VIII.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kynge our ſoueraygne lorde Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye the viij. after the conqueſt, by the grace of God king of England and of Fraunce and lorde of Irelande, at his parlyamente holden at Weſtminſter the iiij. day of Nouember, in the fourh yere of his moſt noble reygne, after the prorogation to the honour of God and holye churche, and for the common weale &amp; profite of this his realme, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the lords ſpiritual and temporall, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in thys preſence parliament aſſembled, &amp; by aucthoritye of the ſame, hath, doo, to be ordeined, made, &amp; enacted, certaine ſtatutes and ordynaunces in maner and fourme folowing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:22324:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N acte concerninge makinge of bulwarkes on the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. Cap. i.</item>
               <item>An act concerning puniſhment for murther. Cap. ii.</item>
               <item>An act concerning iuryes in London. Cap. iij.</item>
               <item>An act of proclamacions to be made before exigents be awarded in forrayne countyes. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An act repelling penaltyes for geuinge of wages to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers and artificers. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>An act concerning cuſtomers &amp; comptrollers for ſealyng of cloth of gold, ſiluer, and al other maner of ſilkes and corſes. Cap. vi.</item>
               <item>An act concerning peuterers, and true weightes &amp; beames. Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>An act concerning Richard Strode. Cap. viii.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS TABVLAE.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22324:2"/>
            <head>HENRICI OCTAVI.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>An act concerning making of Bulwarkes on the ſea ſyde. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rayen the commons in this preſente parliament aſſembled, that for as muche as the lande of Britayne, and alſo the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Breſt lyeth ſtreight agaynſt the South ſea coſtes of the county of Cornewal and that the Frenchmen (our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ennemies) and Britaynes enemyes, by reaſon of their fiſhyng vpon the ſea coſtes, know as well euery hauen and creeke wythin the ſayd countie, as euery la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding place, in as large maner as anye ſubiecte of our ſoueraine lorde the kinges doth. And that the ſayde countye is lxx, myle in length, and the ſubſtaunce thereof righte little more than vi. mile in breade from the ſouth ſea to the north ſea: by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they alſo know that great multitude of people cannot ſhortly reſorte to put them of at their landing: and that in diuers and many of the ſayd lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge places, nother pile, blockhouſe, ne bulwarke is made to greue or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noye them at theyr landing, which conſideracions, vnto our ſaid enemies greate audacitie comforte and courage, geeueth to arriue and lande in the ſame parties, to the great annoyaunce of our ſayd ſouereigne lord his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes there, and to the vtter vndoing of diuers and many of them, vnleſſe a remedy be the ſooner prouided.</p>
               <p>Therefore be it enacted by the king our ſoueraigne lord, his lords ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, &amp; the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled and by auctority of the ſame, that the Iuſtices of the peace and ſheriffe of the ſayd county, do ryde and view all the ſayde South coſte, from Plym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth weſtward to the lands end. And that done, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent to appoint wythin themſelues ſuche boroughes, townes, and paryſhes, as they ſhall thincke reaſonable to make bulwarkes, brayes, walles, ditches, &amp; all other fortifications for the ſame cauſe, in maner, forme, and faſhion, as ſhall bee thoughte by theyr diſcretion in euery of the ſayd landing places betweene this and the fyrſt day of March next now comming. And farther be it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted, by the ſayde auctoritie, that euery Mayre and conſtable of the ſayde countie, by the ſayd Iuſtices of peace or ſheriffe appointed, do commaunde all thinhabitauntes within the precincte of theyr office, to be at the ſea side wyth ſuch inſtrumentes as they haue or can get for the making of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde bulwarkes and other the premiſſes, in ſuch la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding places, as ſhalbe aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſayd Iuſtices of the peace or Sheriffe. And that the ſaid maire or conſtables do commit to warde all ſuch wilfull perſonnes as wyll not obey, come, nor ſende any other perſon to the ſea ſyde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to make the ſaid bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, and other the premiſſes, at the day and time by the ſayde Maire or conſtables to bee appointed, and there to remaine withoute bayle or mainpriſe by the ſpace of tenne dayes or leſſe, at the diſcretion of the ſayde Mayre or Conſtables: And if any of the ſayde Mayres or Conſtables do not their duetie, as is aforeſayd: that than the Iuſticees of the peace nexte
<pb facs="tcp:22324:3"/>
adioyning, do committe to warde the ſame Mayre or Conſtable, ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there to remayne wythoute bayle or maynepryſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or els at the diſcretion of the Iuſtice of peace.</p>
               <p>And alſo be it enacted by the ſaid auctority, that good and ſubſtanciall bulwarkes, braies, walles, ditches, and all other fortifications in euery la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding places (in maner fourme &amp; faſhion as is aforeſaide) as wel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth aforeſayd by the ſea coſtes Eſtward, as in al other parts within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of England, be made there, as the Iuſtices of the peace &amp; Sheriffe within that ſhyre, where any ſuch landing places be, ſhal thincke nedeful. And that euery Iuſtice of peace, Mayre, and conſtable within euery ſhyre, where any ſuche landinge places bee, haue lyke and as good auctority by this preſent acte to commaund the inhabitantes of euery borough, towne, and pariſh adioyninge to the ſea ſyde or els where, after the diſcretions of the Iuſtices of peace, to make the ſayd bulwarkes &amp; other the premiſſes: and alſo commit to warde all ſuch wilfull perſons as will not obey, in like maner as the Iuſtices of the peace, Maires, &amp; conſtables of the ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Cornewall may do by any of the actes aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>And ouer this be it enacted by the ſayde auctority, that it be lawfull for euery of the kynges ſubiectes within this realme of Englande, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and aſſignement of the ſayde Iuſtices of the peace or ſheriffe to make all maner of bulwarkes and other the premiſſes in euery mans grounde, of what eſtate or degree he be of: and alſo to digge and to delue as wel for earth ſtones and turfes, as to cut and to hew heth in any mans grounde for the makynge of any ſuche bulwarkes and other the premiſſes, as ofte and as many times as neede ſhal requyre, and the ſayd erth, ſtones, turfes, and heth to take and occupie and cary awaye oute of the ſaide grounde to any other mans ground, for the making of any ſuch bulwarkes and other the premiſſes: in whoſe ground ſo euer the ſayde earth, ſtones, turfes, and heth happen to bee, wythout any interruption or let of any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being lord or lords of any ſuch ground, or hauinge any other intereſt in the ſame. And without any maner of payment to be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for any of the premiſſes, or any maner of action by any maner or perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, at any time hereafter to be attempted, or in any wyſe mainteyned againſt any of the kinges ſubiectes for any ſuch matter or cauſe. And this acte to endure to the next parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>An act for puniſhment of murther. Cap. ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as robberies, murders &amp; felonies daily encreaſe more and more, and bene committed and done in more heynous open and deteſtable wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ben oft ſeen in times paſt: And the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo offendinge little regarde the puniſhment thereof, by the courſe of the common lawe, ne by reaſon of any ſtatute heretofore made, but beare theim bolde of theyr Clergie, and imagininge and pleadinge of
<pb facs="tcp:22324:3"/>
feygned and vntrue foraine pleas, triable in foraine cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyes, to thinfe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be remoued from place to place, by colourable and vntrue ſuggeſtions and for to be vntruely acquite by fauour might and corrupcion: ſo that they liue in maner without feare or drede. For reformacion wherof, and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth of this realme, and to put the ſayde murderers, felons, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders in more feare and drede ſo to offende: Be it ordeined eſtabliſhed &amp; enacted by the kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, the lordes ſpiritual and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame, that all perſone or perſones, hereafter committinge murder or felony in any churche, chapell, or halowed place, or of and vppon malyce prepenſed, robbe or murder any perſonne or perſonnes in the kinges highe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, or els robbe or murder any perſone in his houſe, the owner or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the houſe, his wife, child, or ſeruaunt than being therin, &amp; put in feare or drede by the ſame, that ſuch perſons ſo offending, be not from henceforth admitted to his or theyr clergy, ſuche as bene within holy orders onelye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte. And ouer that be it enacted by the ſayd auctority, that if any murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer or felon, vpon his arrainment, hereafter do alledge, that he had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye church or churchyard for murder, felonye or other place preueleged for the ſame in a foraine county, and againſt his will taken out thereof: that than the kynges attournay, or any other perſon that will ſue or aledge for the kinge: that the ſayde murderer or felon ſo arayned, was taken at large in the ſame ſhire, where he is ſo arayned: that than the ſame allegeaunce and iſſue to be tried by thenqueſt that ſhould try the ſayd murder or felony within the ſame ſhyre, and before the ſame Iuſtice, where the ſayd murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer or felon is arrained, as though the ſayde forraine plea had not be pleded by the ſayd felon. And if it be founden by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame inqueſt, that the ſayd mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer or felon was taken within the ſame ſhire (as is aforeſayde) that than he to haue none auantage or benefit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter alleged by him for takinge out of the church or churchyard, or other place priuiledged, in any ſuche fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine ſhire. And this acte to endure to the next parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte concerninge Iuries in London. Cap. iij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here at a parlyamente holden at Weſtmin. the .xj. yeare of the reigne of king Henry the .vij. for the good due adminiſtracion and expedition of Iuſtice, it was ordeined, and amonge other thynges enacted, that euery perſon hereafter to be enpanelled or ſommoned to appeare in any Iury or inqueſt, in any courte within the city of London, before any Iudges of the ſame city, making de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault at the firſt ſommons, ſhould loſe &amp; forfaite .xij.d. And at the ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faut .ij.s. And ſo at euery ſuch defaut after that, the iſſues and penalties to be doubled. And alſo ſuch iſſues loſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maires courte ſhould be forfaited leuied, and perceiued to thuſe and behoue of the maire and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comminalty of the ſayd city. And that all ſuch iſſues loſte in the ſheriffes court or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="tcp:22324:4"/>
ſhould be forfayted, leuyed, and perceyued to the vse of the ſheriffes of the ſame city, for the time being, toward their fee ferme, as by the ſame act more plainely doth appeare: in the whiche acte is not expreſſed, howe or by what meanes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayde iſſues, ſo loſt &amp; forfayted, for none appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the perſons ſo impanelled and ſommoned, ſhould be leuied. The lacke whereof is the cauſe, that ſuche perſons as haue bene impanelled and ſommoned, as well for the kinge as betwene party and party (beinge ſubſtanciall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) haue made many tymes defaut, and woulde not appere. And ſo it remaineth in like miſchiefe as it was before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makinge of the foreſayd act, to the greatlet of Iuſtice, and the delaye aſwell in the kynges cauſes, as in other cauſes betwene parties, wherfore for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good execution of the ſaid ſtatute and pertit remedy in this behalfe to be had. Be it eſtabliſhed ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and enacted by the kinge our ſoueraigne lorde by thaſſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſente Parlyamente aſſembled, and by the auctority of the ſame, that for all ſuch iſſues (in forme aforeſaid) hereafter to be loſt or forfaited in the maires court, it ſhalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the ſayde mayre, and to his ſucceſſours, to diſtreine, and the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe to reteine till he or they be ſatiſfied of the ſaid iſſues. And in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that it ſhalbe lawfull to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayd ſheriffes, and their ſucceſſours, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine for ſuche iſſues loſt in their court or courtes, and the ſayd diſtreſſe to reteine till they be ſatiſfied of the ſayde iſſues. Item for as muche as after iſſues ioigned in actions and ſutes commenced taken or dependinge in the kinges courts before hym ſelfe in his bench, and before his Iuſtice of the commen benche: And alſo in his eſcheker at the kynges ſuite, or at the ſuite of the parties triable in the ſayd city of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, as well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge as the parties haue ſuffered great delay many times for defaulte of apparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the iurours impanelled to trye the ſayd iſſues, and many times for lacke of iurours not hauing landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the yerely value, of .xl.s.</p>
               <p>Be it ordeyned and enacted by the ſayd auctority of this preſent parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the ſheriffes of London (for the time beinge) haue full auctority and power to retourne in panelles or arraies of all actions &amp; ſuites nowe dependinge, or that ſhal depend in any of the ſayde courtes or eſcheker, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons beinge citizens hauinge goodes to the value of .C. marke or aboue, to trie the iſſues ioygned or to be ioygned in euery ſuche action or ſuite. And the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo retourned (hauinge goods to the value of .C. marke or aboue) ſhalbe ſworne and do in all ſuch iuries in likewiſe in euery thinge, as other perſons ſhall do hauynge landes and teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the yerely value of .xl.s. ouer all charges. And ouer that be it ordeyned by the ſayde auctority, that the ſheriffes of the ſayd city (for the time beinge) ſhal retourne vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt diſtreſſe in euery ſuch action or ſuite vpon euery of the iuries impanelled to trye the iſſues thereof .xx.d. And vppon the ſeconde diſtreſſe, vpon euery of the ſame iurours .xl.d. And vppon euery diſtreſſe after that, vppon euerye of the ſame Iurours the double, tyll a full Iury in euery ſuch Action and ſuite ſhall appere and be ſworne to trye the iſſues ioygned in the ſame. And
<pb facs="tcp:22324:4"/>
that the ſheriffes, that ſhall make any retourne vpon ſuch diſtreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the fourme aforeſayde, ſhall forfayte for euery ſuche defaulte .x.li. the one halfe thereof to be to the kynge, and the other halfe therof to the party that will ſue therefore. And that the defendaunte in any ſuche action be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to wage his lawe, nor protection therin for him alowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte of proclamations to be made before exigentes be awarded in forraine countries. Cap. iiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, callynge to his moſte gracious remembraunce, howe that before this time dyuers of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this his realme of England, haue bene greuouſly vexed and troubled by reaſon of outlawries had againſt them in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine counties and ſondry action perſonelles, at the ſuite of dyuers maly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons, whyche cruell mynde attempted ſuche actions perſonelles, more for malice than for any iuſte cauſe of action that they had againſt the parties defendauntes named in the ſame. And of the which outlawries ſo had in forraine counties, the partye defendaunte, named in ſuche forrayne actions, had neuer knowledge ne monition, to ſuch time as the outlawrye were agaynſt them had and certified, and ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer came within the countye, where ſuch actions were agaynſte them ſued, ne neuer were dwelling ne conuerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t within the ſayd county. Neuertheleſſe the parties (ſo outlawed in forraine counties) haue loſte their goodes and ſubſtaunce to theyr vtter vndoynge. Wherfore in auoydinge of ſuche malicious and forraine ſuites hereafter to be ſued, the kinge our ſouereigne lord intending the reſtfulnes of his ſayde ſubiectes, and that indifferente Iuſtice ſhoulde be admyniſtred to euerye perſon, as well to the poore as to the ryche, and that euery perſon ſhould haue lawfull knowledge and monition of ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as hereafter be, to be attempted and ſued agaynſte hym in any of the kinges courtes, by the aſſente of the lordes ſpyrytuall and temporall, and the Commons in this preſent Parlyamente aſſembled, and by auctorytye of the ſame, hath ordeined eſtabliſhed and enacted, that from hencefoorthe at the ſame daye that any exigente is awarded or to be awarded agaynſte anye perſon or perſones in anye action perſonell, yf yt dooe appeare by the vſinge of the ſame action, that the partye defendaunt is dwellinge in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countye, than in the ſame countye where the ſame action is ſued: that than the Iuſtices, before whom any ſuch exigend is to be awarded, award one writ of proclamacion, to be direct to the ſheriffe of the counti where it doth appeare by the vſing of ſuch action, that the party defendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the which writ of proclamation ſhal contein theffect of the ſame acty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that the ſheriffe of the countye, to whome any ſuche wryt of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation ſhall bee dyrected, make proclamation .iij. ſeuerall dayes in hys plaine county, whereof one of the ſayd proclamations to be made at the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſeſſions in thoſe parties, wher the ſayd party is ſuppoſed to be dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge,
<pb facs="tcp:22324:5"/>
in that the partye defendaunt yelde him ſelfe to the ſheriffe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine county, to whome any ſuch exigende in any action perſonall ſhall be awarded, ſo that the ſheriffe of ſuche forraine county may vppon hys yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge haue the body of the defendaunte before the Iuſtices, before whom any ſuche exigende is awarded at the day in the ſame exigende compriſed, there to anſwere to the plaintife in the ſame according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. And that euery ſuch writte of proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue the ſame day of returne, as the writ of the exigende vpon ſuch forrayne actions ſo awarded ſhall haue: and that euery ſuch writ of Proclamation be deliuered of recorde to the ſhyryffe or his deputye of the county, into the which any ſuch writ of proclamation is to be awarded. And that the ſheriffe of the ſame county duely execute the ſame, and therof make due retourn at the day in the ſame writ appointed vpon peine to forfaite ſuch amerciament, as by the Iuſtices, before whom ſuch action is vſed, ſhalbe ſeſſed. And that the feliſſour or exige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, in whoſe office ſuch ſute is taken, make out the ſayde writ and writs of proclamaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as after ſhalbe awarded in any of the ſayde courtes. And that the ſame feliſſour or exigenter take no more for the makinge of any ſuch writ of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation and the enteringe of the ſame record, but only ſixe pence.</p>
               <p>And if any outlawry hereafter he had or promulged againſt any perſon or perſons, in any action perſonall in a forraine county, and no writ of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, as is before ſayde awarded, retourned: that than all and euery ſuch outlarie to be vtterly voide and of no force ne effect in the lawe.</p>
               <p>And this acte to beginne and take effect at the feaſte of the Purificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lady ſainct Mary next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge, and not before.</p>
               <p>And alſo be it enacted by the ſayde auctoritye, that in all actions hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be taken in London, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> county of Midd. wherin proceſſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larye lieth agaynſte any perſon or perſons, callinge or naminge theym late of London, that before the exigende be awarded in the ſame action, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partye plaintife or his attourney, after the .iij. capias retourned, ſue a lyke wryt of proclamation, in maner &amp; fourme as is afore ſpecified in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where the ſame perſon or perſons ſo ſued or to be ſued, be conuerſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or dwelling at the time of the ſayd wryt awarded, or els all outlawrys ſo had made pronounced or retourned againſt all ſuche perſons, to be voyde &amp; of none effect. And this acte to endure to the next parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte reapeallinge penalties for geuinge of wages to labourers and artificers. Cap. v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raien the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, that wherfor defaut &amp; lacke of due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſtatute labourers becauſe of a ſtatute and ordinance had and made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xij. yeare of the reigne of kynge Richarde the ſeconde, that geueth penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, peynes and forfaytures agaynſt the Mayſter and geuer, as well as agaynſte Seruauntes, Labourers, Artificers, and craftiſmen, ſo that the
<pb facs="tcp:22324:5"/>
maiſter and giuer for feare therof, dare not put the ſaid eſtatute and other eſtatutes therof made in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherfore by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge our ſoueraigne lord and by thaſſent of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctority of the ſame, be it eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and enacted, that all penaltyes, peynes, and forfaitures conteyned in the ſayd eſtatute, and in all other eſtatutes had &amp; made concerninge ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes labourers of huſbandry, labourers, artificers, and crafteſmen, be onely to and againſt the ſayde maiſter and geuer for henceforth voide &amp; of none effect. And this acte to endure to the next parliament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge cuſtomers and comptrollers for ſealinge of cloth of golde and ſiluer, &amp; all other ſilkes, Cap. vj.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here at a parliament holden in the .xij. yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reygne of king Edwarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiij. amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges other it was ordeined eſtabliſhed and enacted, that the collectours of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidye and the comptrollers. ſhould at all times be redye wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſhould be required, to ſeale any maner of cloth of golde, of ſiluer, baudekin, veluet, damaſke, ſaten, ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenet, Cartron, Chamlette, and euerye other clothe of ſilke, and euery corſe of ſylke and golde, and euery corſe of ſylke of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge beyonde the ſea, and the ſame marchaundiſes ſhoulde ſeale at euery time whan they ſhould be required without delay, taryinge, or any thynge for their ſealinge to take by any meane, vpon the peyne of forfayture to the owner of ſuche marchaundiſes xx.s. by euerye of the ſayde collectours and comptrollers at euery time whan they refuſe to ſeale any ſuch marchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes after ſuche requeſte made, or take any thynge for ſealynge of any ſuche marchandiſes, as by the ſame acte amonges other thynges more playnely appeareth. Sithen the makynge of whiche acte the ſayde collectours and comptrollers, and their clerkes, not fearinge the penaltye limitted in the ſame acte, haue vſed and dayly vſe to take for ſealinge of euery peece of the ſame marchaundiſes, aboue reherſed .ii.d. to the greate hurte and damage of the marchauntes owners of the ſame. For the ſame marchantes at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times bringe &amp; conueighe in one ſhippe .iii. or .iiii. M. peeces of the ſame marchaundyſes, whyche amounteth to .xxx. or .xl.li. after the rate of ii.d. a peece. And for as muche as the foreſayde penaltye, expreſſed in the ſayde ſtatute, is but .xx.s. therefore the ſayde collectours, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptrollers, nor theyr clerkes feare not to runne in ieoperdy of the ſame: wherfore be it ordeined and enacted by the kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, the lordes ſpirituall &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and the commons in this preſent parliamente aſſembled, and by the auctority of the ſame, that from henceforthe the collectours and comptrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the ſayd ſubſidy, nor their clerkes, nor any of them, take for the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of any peece of the ſaid marchandiſes (aboue reherſed) any thing, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peine of forfaiture at euery time .xx.li.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22324:6"/>And alſo be it enacted by the ſame auctoritye, that if and as often as the ſame collectours and comptrollers, or any of them, vnreaſonablye delay or tary the ſayd marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or any of them, for and about the ſealinge of the ſame marchandiſes: that than and as often the ſame collectours and comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo vnreaſonably delaying and taryinge the ſame marchantes, or any of them, to forfait for the ſame .xl.s. The one moite of euery of the ſayd penalties (ſo forfaited) to bee to the kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, and the other moity thereof to the marchaunte ſo greeued, that will ſue for the ſame by way of information in the kinges eſchequer, or by actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or byll of debte after the order of the common lawe, as in other actions of debt is vſed: in whyche action the defendant ſhal not be admitted to wage his lawe, nor protection, nor eſſoyne to be to him allowed in the ſame ſuite, for the ſaid forfaiture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶An acte concerninge peuterers and true weightes and beames Cap. vij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuche as a certaine acte was made and eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter the .xix. yere of the reigne of the late moſt famous king youre father Henry the .vij. whom god pardon, concernynge peauterets, and braſiers, hauking and walkinge about the countreis, and alſo concerning falſe beames, ſcales and weightes, with a prouiſion for caſting of fine met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and of perfit goodneſſe: Whiche acte was made to endure to the next Parliamente, the tenour whereof hereafter enſueth: That where manye ſimple and euill diſpoſed perſons of this your realme of England (vſynge the ſayde craftes) dayelye goe aboute this your realme from village, from towne, and from houſe to houſe, as well in woddes and foreſtes, as other places, to bye peauter and braſſe, and that knowynge, theues and other pickets, that ſteale as well peuter and braſſe, belongynge to youre hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and vnder youre marke, and to the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, as to your ſubiectes of this your realme, bringe ſuch ſtolen veſſels vnto them in ſuch hid places to ſell, and ſell it for litle or nought, and about they bring it to priuye places, or into corners of cities or townes, and there ſell muche part of it to ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, the which cary it ouer the ſea by ſtelth. Alſo the ſayd perſons (ſo goinge aboute) and diuers other vſinge the ſayde craftes, vſe to make newe veſſels, and mixe good mettall and bad together, and make it nought, and ſell it for good ſtuffe, where in deed the ſtuffe and mettal ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is not worth the fourth party that is ſolde for, to the great hurt, diſceipte and loſſe of your ſubiectes. Alſo dyuers perſons, vſynge the ſayde craftes, haue diſceyuable and vntrue beames and ſcales, that one of theym wyll ſtande euen wyth .xij.li. weyghte at the one ende, agaynſte a quarter of a pounde at the other ende, to the ſynguler aduauntage of them ſelfe, and to
<pb facs="tcp:22324:6"/>
the great diſceite and loſſe of your ſubiectes, biers and ſellers wyth them. For reformacion of the premiſſes it woulde pleaſe your highnes of your moſt aboundant grace, with thaduiſe of your lords ſpyrituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſente parliamente aſſembled, &amp; by auctoritye of the ſame, to enacte and eſtabliſhe, that no perſon nor perſons, vſyng the ſayde craftes of peauterers and braſiers, from henceforth ſhall ſell or chaunge any peauter or braſſe, newe or olde, at any place or places within this your realme, but onely in open fayres or markettes, or in theyr owne dwellinge houſes, but if they be deſyred by the ſand biers of ſuch wares, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon payne of forfaytuee to our ſouereigne lord the king for euery ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault x.li. Alſo by the ſame auctoritie it may be enacted and eſtabliſhed, that no perſon nor perſons, of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion or degree ſoeuer he or they be from henceforth within the citie of London and Yorke, or wythout either caſte or woorke any pewter veſſels or braſſe at any place or places within this your realme, but that it be as good fine metall, as is the peauter and braſſe caſte and wrought after the perfect goodnes of the ſame, wythin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cittie of London, &amp; by the ſtatutes of the ſame owe to be, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiture of all ſuch peauter and braſſe, ſo caſt &amp; wroughte of worſe peauter or braſſe than ought to be wrought in the ſame cities: the one halfe of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch forfaiture to be to the vſe of your highnes, and the other halfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the finders thereof.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this forfaiture in no wiſe ſtretch ne extend to braſſe or peauter, being in the poſſeſſion of any perſon, other than the workers of the ſame, or ſuch as haue the ſame to ſell, and beinge of the craftes or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie. Alſo that it may by the ſame auctoritie be enacted and eſtabliſhed, that no maner of perſon or perſons, of what degree or condicion ſoeuer he or they be, from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth make no hollow wares of peauter, that is to ſay ſaltes and pottes, that is made of peauter called laye mettall, but that it may be after thaſſiſe of peauter laie mettal wrought wythin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> makers of ſuch wares ſhall marke the ſame wyth ſeueral markes of theyr owne, to the entent that the makers of ſuch wares ſhall auow the ſame wares by them (as is aboueſayd) to be wrought. And that al and euery ſuch wares, not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly made and wrought, and not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in forme aboueſayd founde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the poſſeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maker or ſeller to be forfayted: and if the ſame ware be ſolde, the ſayd maker to forfait the value of the ſame ſo vnlawfully wrought and ſould, the one halfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid wares, or the value thereof, to be the vſe of your highnes, and the other halfe to be to the vſe of the finder or ſerchers of the ſame. Alſo that it may by the ſayd auctority be enacted and eſtablyſhed, that if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereafter, vſyng bying and ſelling of peauter or braſſe, that hereafter occupy any diſceiuable or falſe beames or weightes of the ſaid wares, that euery ſuche perſon or perſons, vſynge or occupyinge ſuche dyſceyuable and vntrue beames or weyghtes, to forfaite .xx.s. the one half to the kynge, and the other halfe to the partye that therefore ſhall ſue by action
<pb facs="tcp:22324:7"/>
of det: and that in the ſaid action no protection nor eſſoyne ſhalbe allowed. And alſo the ſayde party ſo offendings, ſhall forfaite his beame to him that ſhall ceaſe it: and if the ſayd offender or offenders be not ſufficiente to pay the ſayde ſomme or ſommes by theym ſo forfayted, that then it ſhall bee lawfull to the Mayres, bayliffes, or other heade officers of ſuche place or places, where any ſuch offenders ſhalbe found to put them in the ſtockes, and them ſo to kepe till y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next market day next adioyning, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> market place to put them in the pillorie all the market time. And furthermore that it be lawfull by the ſayd auctority, that the maiſter &amp; wardeins of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde craft of peuterers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in euery citie and borough of this realme, where ſuch wardeins are, and where no ſuch wardens are, the head officers or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame citie or borough, to appoint certeyne perſons moſt expert in knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, to make ſerch within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd citties or boroughes where they dwell. And ouer this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſtices of peace within euery ſhyre at the generall ſeſſions holden at Mighelmas, ſhal aſſigne and appoint two certaine perſons, hauing experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therin, to make ſerch in the premiſſes in euery part of that ſhire, as well within the frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches as without, ſauing in cities or borowes, wher ſerchers be appointed by the heds or gouernours of the ſame. And that all ſuch vnlawfull peauter or braſſe, as the ſayd ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhall find, the one halfe to the vſe of your grace, and the other half to the ſaid ſerchers. And that in the defaute of the ſaid maiſters &amp; wardeins of the ſayd occupacions, not ſerching informe as is aforeſayd, and wherby that any ſuch vnlawfull mettels is caſte or made, or vnlawfull weightes vſed: that then it ſhalbe lawfull to any perſon or perſons, hauing ſufficient cunninge &amp; knowledge in the ſaid occupacions, by ouerſight of the maire bayliffes, or heade officers of the ſayde citties, boroughes and townes, to ſearch al the ſayd places, and to put ſayd auctoritie and acte in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in forme aforeſayd. Pleaſeth it therfore your grace and wyſedomes, in ſo much as the ſayd acte is thought good and profitable, that it be ordeyned enacted and eſtabliſhed, by the lordes ſpyrituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſente parliamente aſſembled, and by the auctority of the ſame, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd act may endure for euer. And ouer that be it enacted by the ſayde auctority, that if any vntrue or deceyuable mettell or worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of Tinne or peauter, be founden either in platters, chargers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, ſaucers, potengers, trenchers, baſins, flagons, bottels, pottes, ſalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, goblettes, ſpones, cruettes, or candelſtickes, or any other ſuche wares of tinne or peauter, whereſoeuer it be caſt, made, or wroughte wythin this realme or wythout, and brought to be ſould within the ſame realme: that than it ſhal be lawful to the mayre of the cittie of London, and the maiſter and warde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the craft of peauterers (of the ſayd city for the time being) and theyr deputies, to haue ſerch of the ſame wythin the cittie of London, and the ſuburbes of the ſame. And that in all other citties, boroughes, and townes, where any wardeins bee or ſhall bee, the Mayres, baylif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, or heade officers, and wardeynes to haue like aucthoritie. And
<pb facs="tcp:22324:7"/>
where no wardeins be, than the head officers or gouernours of the ſame citties, boroughes, and townes to appoint certaine perſons moſt experte &amp; cunning in knowledge of the ſame, to make ſerch wythin the ſayd cities, boroughes and townes where they dwell. And if any ſuch new wares wrought of tinne and peauter, as is aforeſayd, be found defectiſe, &amp; beinge in the poſſeſſion of the ſellar, that then ſame perſon or perſon that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any ſuch newe wares of peauter to ſale, ſhall forfaite the ſame wares, the one halfe to the vſe of our ſoueraigne lord the king, and the other halfe to the ſerchers or finders of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Prouided alway that this act concerning the forfayture be not preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall nor hurtfull to any perſon or perſons, hauing grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſoueraigne lord the kinge, or of any of his noble progenitours by his letters patents of ſuch forfayture, but that they and euery of them ſhal &amp; may enioy the ſame according to theyr former grauntes and libertyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>An act concerning Richard Strode. Cap. viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Amentably complayneth &amp; ſheweth vnto your moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete wyſedomes in this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Strode gentleman of the county of Deuonſhyre, one of the burgeis of this honourable houſe, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burghe of Plimton in the countie aforeſayd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Richard condeſcended and greed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other of this houſe, to put forth certeine villes in this preſent parliament againſt certaine perſons, named tinners in the countie aforeſaid, for the reformacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> periſhing, hurting, and deſtroying of diuers portes, hauens, and creekes, and other villes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale of the ſayd countie, the which here in this high court of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhould and ought to be commended and treated of.</p>
               <p>And for becauſe the ſaid Richard is a tinner, for the cauſes and matters afore reherſed, one Iohn Furſe tinner, vnderſtewarde of the Steimerie in the ſayd countie, in and at foure courtes of the ſayd Steimerie at diuers places and times before him ſeuerally holden in the ſayde county, he and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue condempned the ſayd Richarde in the ſomme of clx.li. That is to wete at euery court day xl.li. and that by the procurement of the ſaid Iohn Furſe, at the ſayde foure ſeuerall courtes and lawdayes, in the ſayd Stey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merie by him holden, in this maner publiſhed and ſayde, that the ſame Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard at the laſt parliament holden at Weſtminſter, woulde auoyded and vtterly deſtroyed all liberties, priuiledges, &amp; frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches concerning the Stei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merie: by reaſon whereof the ſayde Richarde, vppon foure billes had and made therof by the ſayd Iohn Furſe and other, cauſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd Richard was preſented &amp; founden giltie of the premiſſes in euery of the ſayde cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in xl.li. to be loſte and forfaite by him, by reaſon of an acte and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce by tinners made and had at a place in the ſayde countie called Crokerentor: the tenour of the which acte appeareth in Cedule to this bill
<pb facs="tcp:22324:8"/>
annexed: to the which the ſayd Richarde was neuer warned nor called to make anſwere to the premiſſes, contrary to al lawes, right reaſon, &amp; good conſcience. And for the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, one Iohn Agwilliam vpon a ſurmiſe by him made to the kinges highnes to the ſayd condempnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be to his grace forfaite, therof attainted a bill aſſigned of xx.li. percel of the ſayd clx.li. to be to him graunted by the ſayd kyngs highnes: whereupon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Iohn Agwilliam and other cauſed the ſayd Richard was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſoned in a dongeon and a deepe pitte vnder the ground in the caſtel of Lidford in the ſayde county, and there &amp; els where remayned by the ſpace of thre weekes &amp; more, vnto ſuch time he was deliuered by a writ of priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings eſchequere at Weſtminſter, for that hee was one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> collectours in the ſayd countie for the fyrſt of the two quindeims grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at and in this preſent parliamente: the which priſon is one of the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noious, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious, &amp; dteteſtable places wythin this realme: ſo that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſame impryſonment he was put in great parell &amp; ieoperdy of his life, and the ſayd Richard ſo being in pryſon, and the ſaid Iohn Agwilliam ſeing the ſame cruell impryſonment of the ſayd Richard, entreated and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly deſyred one Philip Furſe) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being keper of the ſaid pryſon) ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to kepe the ſaid Richard in pryſon, &amp; to put yrons vpon him to his more greater payne &amp; ieoperdy, and to giue him but breade and water onely, to thentent to cauſe the ſayd Richard to be faine to content &amp; pay him the ſaid xx.li. And for the ſame promiſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd keeper foure markes of money: for the which foure markes the ſayd Rychard for to be eaſed of his yrons and peyneful impryſonment aforeſayd (for ſauegarde of his life) promiſed and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to pay the ſayd keeper foure marke: wherof he payed the ſayd ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in hand xiii.s.iiii d. And ouer that the ſayd Richarde for to be eaſed of his ſayd paynefull impryſonment, was alſo of neceſſity driuen to be boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to Thomas Denis, deputy vnto ſir Henry Marney knighte, warden of the ſaid Steimerie, in an obligation of the ſomme of C.li. Vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereof party is as hereafter followeth: that is to ſaye, that if the aboue bounden Richard Strode, defende and ſaue harmeles the ſayde Thomas Denis, and to vſe himſelfe as true pryſoner, duringe the tyme it ſhall pleaſe the kyng to haue him pryſoner in the caſtel of Lidforde, and alſo to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, wherby he ſhall in the law be deemed out of priſon, &amp; other articles compriſed in the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion, the which the ſayd Richard perfectly reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not: wherfore the premiſſes by your great wyſedomes tenderly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, the ſaid Richard humbly prayeth, that it may be ordeyned, eſtabliſhed and enacted, by the kynge our ſoueraigne lorde, and by the lords ſpyrituall and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctority of the ſame, that the ſaid condemnacion and condemnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſaid clx.li. and euery parcell thereof, and iudgementes and executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had or to be had for the premiſſes or any of them, to be vtterly voyd againſt the ſaid Richard and of none effect.</p>
               <p>And ouer that be it enacted by the ſaid auctoritie, that all ſuites, accuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb facs="tcp:22324:8"/>
condemnacions, executions, fines, amercementes, puniſhmentes, corrections, grauntes, charges, and impoſicions put or had, or hereafter to be put or had vnto or vpon the ſayd Richard, and to euery other of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons afore ſpecifyed, that now be of this preſent parliament, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of any parliament hereafter ſhalbe, for any bill, ſpeaking, reaſoning, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring of any matter or matters, concerning the parliament to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and treated of, be vtterly voyde and of none effect.</p>
               <p>And ouer that be it enacted by the ſayd auctority, that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Richard Strode, or any of all the ſayd other perſon or perſons, hereafter be vexed, troubled, or otherwyſe charged for any cauſes, as is aforeſayd, that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he or they and euery of them ſo vexed or troubled, of and for the ſame, to haue action vpon the caſe agaynſt euery ſuch perſon or perſonnes, ſo vexinge or troubling any contrary to this ordinaunce and prouiſion, in the which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the party greeued ſhall recouer treble damages and coſtes. And that no perotection, eſſoyne, nor wager of law in the ſayd action in any wyſe be admitted nor receyued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enquyred for our ſoueraigne lord the king, that where as at the parliament holden at Crokere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tor, before Thomas De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, deputie to ſyr Henry Marney knight, warde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Stei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merie, the xiiij. day of September, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yere of the reigne of king Henry the viii. It was ordeyned eſtabliſhed and enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that (from the day aforeſayd) it ſhalbe lawfull for euery man to digge tinne within the county of Deuonſhyre, in all places where as tinne may be founden. And alſo to carie the water to theyr workes without any let or trouble of any perſon or perſons, according to our vſages &amp; confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our charter, &amp; according to our cuſtome out of minde. And if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſonnes let, trouble, or vexe any man to digge tinne, or to cary water for the ſame, contrary to our olde cuſtome and vſage, and if it be founden by verdite of xii. men at the law day, he that ſo letteth, vexeth, or troubleth any ſuch perſon or perſonnes, ſhall fall in the penaltie of xl.li. as oft as he ſo vexeth or troubleth: the one halfe to my lord Prince, and the other halfe to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſo letted, vexed, or troubled. And a Fieri facias to be awarded, as well for my lord prince as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> party, if one Richard Strode of Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton tinner, at the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t holden at Weſtminſter the fourth day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary laſt paſt, letted, vexed, and troubled one William Rede the yonger, and Elis Elforde tinner, and al other tinners in the ſame parliamente for digging of tinne in the ſeuerall ſoyle of the ſayd Richard and other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contrary to this our acte made.</p>
               <closer>God ſaue the king.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
